Here we are back in Colab, looking at the week seven, day five of the Colab notebooks and I'm on a
콜랍에 돌아왔어요 콜랍 공책 대회 7주 차 5일째예요 T4 박스에 탔는데
T4 box, so it's a low end cheap box.
저렴한 싸구려 박스죠
That's all that's required since we are doing inference today, not training.
훈련이 아니라 추론하는 거니까 그것만 하면 돼요
Um, or the training is still happening in this other tab, as you can see.
아니면 훈련이 다른 탭에서 진행되거나요
Uh, as, as as we speak, uh, we start with a few installs and then some imports with the usual kind
말씀드리는 순간 설치 몇 개로 시작해서 늘 하던 대로 가져오기로 했어요
And let me just tell you about the constants that we've got here.
여기 있는 상수에 대해 말씀드릴게요
Um, the base model, of course, llama 3.1 project name is Preiser, the hugging face user.
기본 모델은 라마 3이고요 프로젝트 이름은 포옹하는 얼굴 사용자 프리저예요
So you choose here, you can put in.
여기서 선택해 put in을 해요
Well, I hope that you'll be putting in your name and you'll be running this inference, this test against
여러분의 이름을 입력하고 모델에 대한 추론과 테스트를 실행해 주세요 여러분이
the model that you have fine tuned and uploaded to the Hugging Face Hub.
잘 조율해서 Hub에 업로드한 모델이죠
It is possible, though, that you have, uh, either, uh, lost patience and or you just want to see
하지만 인내심을 잃으셨거나 제 테스트 결과가 궁금하신 거라면 제 이름은
how my one did, in which case you can keep my name in there because this model will be public.
그대로 두셔도 돼요 이 모델은 공개될 테니까요
So you will be able to run against this model too.
이 모델에 맞서 달릴 수 있어요
Um, and I've selected in here the run name.
그리고 실행 이름을 선택했어요
This is the run name.
이게 실행명이에요
You may recognize that that 39 there is the run name in hugging face of the one that I ran for multiple
39가 뭔지 아실 겁니다 제가 과거에 여러 개국 시대에 사용한 포옹의
epochs in the past.
연계명이죠
Um, and this revision, this is where I am specifying which of the different checkpoints I am selecting.
이 수정본은 제가 어떤 체크포인트를 선택할지 지정하는 곳이죠
I'm selecting the one before it started to badly overfit.
너무 과해지기 전에 골라야 해요
Um, and this was the one where it was still getting good, good results.
이 영화는 여전히 좋은 결과가 나오고 있었어요
Um, and then this becomes the name of my fine tuned model.
그리고 이게 제 미세 튜닝 모델의 이름이 되죠
It is, of course, the hugging face name.
당연히 포옹하는 얼굴 이름이죠
I'm sorry.
미안해요
I should make this, uh.
이걸 만들어야겠어요
Otherwise, I'm hard coding my name in here.
안 그러면 제 이름을 하드 코딩해야 해요
But what I'll do is I will make two versions of this.
하지만 전 두 가지 버전을 만들 거예요
One will be for the hugging face user that you have entered in.
하나는 여러분이 입력한 포옹 얼굴 유저예요
And the other one I will comment out and I will say uncomment this line if you should use my model.
다른 건 주석 처리로 이 라인을 주석 처리 해제하라고 하죠 제 모델을 사용한다면요
Uh, and either of course, if you're using your model, you'll need to change the run name and the
물론 모델을 사용한다면 실행명과 개정도 바꿔야 합니다 여러분이 사용하는
revision to match whatever you're using.
것에 맞추기 위해서요
And you can start by not putting in put revision equals none.
for reision = 0을 입력하지 않는 것부터 시작하세요
Um, or revision equals none if you're not using a revision at all okay.
수정 = 0일 수도 있고요 수정 을 사용하지 않는다면 말이죠
And then for the data set uh, either again we load in the data set that you have carefully, lovingly
그리고 데이터 세트에서는 여러분이 정성껏 정리해서 업로드한 데이터 세트를 다시 로드합니다
curated and uploaded to the Huggingface hub.
허깅페이스 허브에 말이죠
Uh, or you can just use my one should you prefer.
아니면 제 걸 쓰셔도 돼요
Um, and now and by the way, if you have gone with the lower cost version of this and you've trained
음, 그런데 만약 이것의 저비용 버전을 선택하고 가전제품 전용
your model for appliances only for home appliances, then of course you should be filling in the light
가전제품 모델을 훈련시켰다면 당연히 여러분이 구축한 라이트
data set that you'll have built and your model for for home appliances, and you will get similar kinds
데이터 세트와 가전제품 모델을 채워야 합니다 그럼 비슷한 결과가 나오죠
Quant for bit is true.
비트라는 퀀트는 진실이에요
We are quantizing and then you may remember these are the nice ways that we can print colorful lines
수량화하는 거죠 기억하실지 모르겠지만 색색의 선을 출력하는 좋은
to the output.
방법들이에요
Okay.
네
Then we log in to hugging face.
얼굴 포옹에 로그인해요
You're used to this now.
이제 익숙해졌잖아요
We don't need to log into weights and biases because we're not training.
훈련이 아니니까 무게나 편향에 로그인할 필요 없어요
And then we load in the data set.
그런 다음 데이터 세트를 로드하죠
And as well, you know, at this point if I look at the first training data set, we won't be using
그리고 지금 이 시점에서 첫 번째 훈련 데이터 세트를 보면 더는 사용하지 않을
it anymore.
거예요
But it has the price baked into it.
하지만 가격이 들어 있어요
It looks like this.
이렇게 생겼어요
We will of course now be using the test data set which looks like this.
물론 테스트 데이터 세트를 사용할 겁니다 이렇게 생겼죠
The text does not have the price.
텍스트에는 가격이 없어요
The price is only in the answer which is not given to the model.
가격은 모델에 없는 답안에만 달려 있어요
It's only given this text as well.
이 문장만 있어요
You can double triple check in a moment when we get to the part that we'll be actually doing this prediction,
비트 박스를 만들 때 다시 한번 확인해 주세요 비트 박스를 만들 때
It would be a bit of a gaffe, wouldn't it, if we were accidentally passing in the price itself?
가격표를 실수로 넘기면 실수가 되겠죠?
But we're not.
하지만 우린 아니죠
Okay, so then first of all, it's time to it's time to load in our tokenizer and our fine tuned model.
좋아요, 그럼 먼저 토큰라이저와 미세 튜닝 모델을 로드할게요
So we first pick the right kind of quantization.
먼저 올바른 양자화를 선택해요
You're familiar with this same as before.
예전과 같은 방식이죠
This is also the same as before.
이것도 예전과 똑같아요
Well with a slight difference just here.
여기만 살짝 달라요
But we load in the tokenizer.
토큰이저도 설치했어요
We put in that boilerplate stuff to set up some of its parameters.
매개 변수를 설정하기 위해 상용 문서를 넣었어요.
We load in the base model as before using the right quant config.
올바른 퀀트 구성을 사용하기 전처럼 베이스 모델을 로드하죠
And we have got that one liner again.
또 한 줄짜리 대사가 나왔네요
And now this is new.
이건 새로운 거예요
So we are now loading something called a left model.
이제 왼쪽 모델이라는 걸 로드하고 있어요
If you remember stands for parameter efficient fine tuning.
매개 변수 효율 미세 조정의 약자란 걸 기억하세요
It's the name of the package which which which has coded Laura.
로라를 암호화한 상자 이름이에요
So a left model represents it's a hugging face model that represents a model that has a base.
왼쪽 모델은 안아주는 얼굴 모델이고 베이스 모델을 나타내요
And then it's got some adapter applied on top of the base.
밑부분에는 어댑터가 달려 있어요
And so that is what we load.
이걸 로딩할 거예요
Now you call that with Frompretrained.
Frompretled이라고 부르는군요
And you can pass in the base model, the fine tuned model name which we set up above.
그리고 위에서 설정한 미세 튜닝 모델 이름을 베이스 모델로 넘길 수 있어요
And then a revision if you wish.
원하시면 복습도 가능해요
So if revision is not null none then I pass it in.
수정값이 0이 아니면 넘기는 거죠
Otherwise we just don't don't don't bother passing it in.
안 그러면 전달할 필요가 없죠
Um and so that will load in our fine tuned model.
미세 튜닝 모델에 로드될 거예요
And at the end of that we'll print the memory footprint.
마지막에 메모리 발자국을 프린트할 거예요
You may remember the memory footprint was what, 5.6GB before and now it is 5.7.
메모리 발자국이 5개였던 거 기억하시죠? 전에는 6GB였는데 지금은 5GB예요 7시요
It's 5700MB because there's that extra 100MB or 109MB of our Laura adapters.
5700MB인 이유는 로라 어댑터가 100이나 109MB 더 있기 때문이죠
Um, our Laura A's and Laura B's in there.
로라 A와 로라 B가 있어요
Uh, one more time, we can just print this fine tuned model.
미세 튜닝 모델로 한 번 더 프린트할게요
You may remember we did this right back in week.
기억하실지 모르겠지만 주중에 이걸 했어요
Uh, in day two, when I mentioned we were, we were taking a look into the future because I was using
둘째 날, 제가 미래를 보고 있다고 했죠 이걸 사용하고 있었거든요
this.
이 모형은 우리가 봤던 거예요
And this is how it appears.
이렇게 보이죠
If you remember this, you can see all the different layers of the neural network, and you can see
이걸 기억하시면 신경망의 다양한 층이 보입니다
that when you get to these, the, the tension layers, that there's a dropout layer in there.
여기 장력 층을 보면 드롭아웃 층이 있어요 Get up
Now, you know all about dropout with 10% probability of dropouts.
자퇴 확률 10%에 대해 잘 아시죠?
And then there's Laura A and Laura B that are in there as well.
로라 A와 로라 B도 있어요
Um, and uh, yeah, you can see that Laura A and Laura B are for all of the layers that have been adapted,
로라 A와 로라 B는 각 층을 나타내는 거예요 우리의 목표
our target modules.
모듈이죠
And you also worth just noting down at the very end here, the LM head, since I just talked about that,
그리고 여기 끝에 LM헤드도 주목해 주세요. 방금 이야기
this is the final, uh, the, the, the final fully connected layer that outputs the logits, the number
했듯이 완전히 연결된 마지막 레이어에서 로지트와 가능한 보캡 토큰 보캡 항목의
for each of the possible, uh, vocab token vocab entries, um, which will then go into a softmax in
숫자를 출력합니다. 그리고 소프트맥스로 가서 다음 토큰의 가능성을
order to predict the probability of the next token.
예측하죠.
All right.
좋아요
Are you ready?
준비됐어요?
So, uh, we're going to go in and run inference.
그래서 추론을 실행할 거예요
Uh, the, uh, I want to give you one more time, a quick, uh, memory that GPT four zero got to $76
한 번 더 빠르게 설명하고 싶은데요 GPT 40이 76 라마 3으로 바뀌었다는
llama 3.1 base model.
메모리를요 기본 모델 1개요
This this untrained model was $396.
이 미숙련 모델은 396달러였어요
Very disappointing.
정말 실망스럽네요
Uh, this human being here got 127, uh, as my error, uh, and very much hoping to see that llama
여기 이 사람은 제 오류로 127점을 받았어요 라마가 사람을 이길 수 있는지
can beat a human.
보고 싶어요
Um, as an open source model, it is important to keep in mind I don't, uh, in case you're expecting
오픈 소스 모델로서 명심해야 할 점은 여러분이 여기서 터무니없는 걸 기대하실까
something, uh, crazy here, that prices of things have a lot of volatility, and the model doesn't
봐 말씀드리는데 가격이 많이 변동될 수 있는데 모델은 그에 대해 아무것도 몰라요
It's not going to know if the price of a product has been slashed, uh, because it's on sale by by
제품 가격이 급락했는지도 알 수 없습니다. 엄청난 가격으로 판매되고 있으니까요.
So there is a natural big variation in these product prices, as I discovered when I was trying to do
제품 가격에는 자연적으로 큰 차이가 있어요 제가 직접 만들어
it for myself and got wildly out.
보려 했을 때 알게 된 사실이죠
This is this is it's a very difficult challenge.
이건 아주 어려운 과제예요
You might think that it sounds like a it's not that hard.
별로 어렵지 않다고 생각할 수도 있어요
It is very hard.
정말 힘들어요
Try it for yourself and you'll see.
직접 해 보면 알 거예요
Um, okay.
네
With that caveat in mind, let's keep going.
그 점을 명심하고 계속하죠
So extract price is the function that you, you know, well it takes a string, it looks for price is
가격 추출 함수는 아시다시피 문자열이 있죠 가격 이즈 달러를 찾아요
dollars.
그 다음에 나오는 숫자를 한 번 더 찾아보죠 스스로 만족하도록 가격을
extract price and put in a string.
추출해 문자열을 만들어보죠.
Price is dollars a fabulous, uh, eight, nine nine, 99 or so, whatever I want to say and out comes
가격은 달러입니다 아주 멋진 달러죠 8, 9, 99, 그쯤 돼요 제가 말하고 싶은 대로 가격을 말하죠
Uh, I'm sure you get it.
I'm get you're know
Uh, so that's extract price.
이게 추출가예요
Uh, and then this is the model predict function, the function that we used before, um, that takes
그리고 이건 모델 예측 함수입니다 전에 사용했던 함수로
the the inputs.
입력을 받죠
Um, that takes the attention mask.
그건 관심 마스크를 쓴 거죠
Is that thing I told you about that you use to avoid it?
혹시 제가 말씀드린 그거 피하시는 거예요?
Throwing a warning and to make it very clear that we don't need it to predict the the most of the input
입력 프롬프트를 예측하기 위해 필요한 것은 아니라는 것을 확실히 하기 위해 경고를
prompt.
던지죠
Um, and then the outputs we call generate on the, on the fine tuned model, we pass in the inputs.
미세 조정 모델에서 발생하는 출력은 입력값을 전달하죠
We pass in this attention mask, we only need up to three new tokens because we're going to get the
주의 마스크를 통과시킵니다. 새로운 토큰 세 개만 있으면 됩니다. 왜냐하면 다음 토큰은 우리가 정말
the next token is really going to be the one that we care about.
중요하게 생각하는 것이기 때문이죠.
But we'll, we'll put in some more just to make sure if, if it makes some horrible mistake that we
하지만 만약 끔찍한 실수를 저지르면 그걸 포착하기 위해 몇
capture that, um, and then we take, we say only one response, please, we take that one response
가지 더 입력할 거예요 그리고 답변을 하나만 받아내죠 그 답변 하나만 받아내서
and we extract the price.
가격을 추출해요
Now, as it happens, we can do a little bit better than this prediction function.
비트만 있으면 이 예측 함수보다 좀 더 잘할 수 있어요
This doesn't make a whole massive amount of difference.
큰 차이는 없어요
But but since, since, since we've got so much control over this model, we can actually do something
하지만 이 모델에 대한 컨트롤이 아주 많기 때문에 다음 토큰을 다루는
a bit smarter with how we handle this next token.
방법에 대해 좀 더 현명한 비트를 할 수 있어요
And so I've written this function.
그래서 이 함수를 작성했어요
That's an improved model predict function.
향상된 모델 예측 함수죠
Improved model predict uh which is um, yeah.
향상된 모델 예측 결과 네
It's just um, it's a bit more involved.
비트가 좀 더 복잡해요
So, um, I guess, uh, I'll, uh, I'll just explain it in simple terms, but it's not super important.
그러니까 간단히 설명할게요 하지만 그렇게 중요한 건 아니에요
What it does is instead of just taking the most likely next token, it takes the most likely three next
가장 가능성이 높은 다음 토큰이 아니라 가장 가능성이 높은
tokens, the three with the highest probability.
세 개의 토큰을 취하는 거죠
Uh, and then it says, okay, what probability did you give for these three.
이 세 가지의 확률은 어떻게 나왔나요?
And they represent real numbers.
실제 숫자를 나타내죠
Like maybe you said it was very likely to be worth $100 and then a little bit less likely to be 99,
가령, 비트 상자가 100달러쯤 되고 99$보다는 조금 적고 101$쯤
but a lot more likely to be 101.
될 거라고 했죠
But 100 was the most.
근데 100이 제일 높았어요
And then it just takes a weighted average between those three numbers.
그런 다음 그 세 숫자 사이에 가중된 평균을 얻어요
And that's a way for us to get a little bit more precise about what's it trying to predict.
비트가 뭘 예측하려 하는지 좀 더 정확하게 알아낼 수 있는 방법이죠
Um, and it allows it to predict something that's not necessarily always a whole number.
그리고 항상 숫자가 전부인 건 아니지만 예측할 수 있게 해주죠
Um, so it's a it's a technique I've used.
제가 사용한 기술이에요
It's sort of solving for the fact that we're treating what is really a regression problem as a classification
분류 문제로서 퇴행 문제를 치료하고 있다는 사실을 해결하는
problem.
거죠
It's not super important that you know about this, but but and it doesn't make much difference if you
이걸 아는 게 그리 중요하진 않지만 위의 함수를 사용한다고 크게
use the function above.
달라지진 않아요
It just makes a bit of difference.
비트가 약간 달라요
But it is maybe worth looking through this if you're interested in these last layers of the neural network,
신경망의 마지막 계층에 관심이 있다면 한 번 살펴보는
because you can see that what I do is I take the outputs of the fine tuned model passing in the inputs,
게 좋을 것 같습니다. 왜냐하면 미세하게 조정한 모델이 입력을 통과하면
and these are considered the the logits that I mentioned this vector across all of the possible vocabulary
출력을 얻고 이것들은 로그잇으로 간주됩니다. 토큰라이저의 가능한 어휘 엔트리에 걸쳐 있는
entries for a tokenizer.
벡터죠.
And then I call softmax in order to convert that into probabilities.
그런 다음 소프트맥스를 호출해 확률로 전환하죠
And then I go through the top three.
그리고 상위 3인에 들죠
And I just this is some some gumph that just takes the weighted average between those top three.
그리고 이 검프라는 게 상위 3위의 평균을 가늠하는 거예요
It's weighted prices and sums up the weighted prices.
가격도 중대하고 가격도 중대해요
And that's what it returns.
그게 반환되죠
So it's very similar to model predict.
모델 예측과 아주 유사하죠
It just gives a slightly more accurate answer that's based on the top three predictions, not just the
좀 더 정확한 답을 제공할 뿐이죠 최고의 예측이 아니라 상위 3개 예측에
top prediction.
근거해서요
Uh, and so then we have our class tester.
그리고 우리 반 테스터도 있어요
This is just exactly the same tester class that we've used before.
이건 우리가 전에 사용했던 테스터 클래스와 정확히 같아요
Um, and it is worth just pointing out that the thing I mentioned before this, this is obviously this
제가 전에 언급했던 것을 짚고 넘어가야 할 것 같아요 이게 전체의
is the meat of the whole thing.
핵심이에요
When we take whatever functions passed in and we call it, and what we pass in is only the text associated
통과한 함수를 취하고 호출할 때 통과하는 건 데이터 포인트와 관련된 텍스트예요
We obviously don't tell it the price.
가격은 당연히 안 알려줘요
All it knows is the text, uh, so that it doesn't have any knowledge of the price.
문자만 알고 있어서 가격은 전혀 몰라요
Of course, of course.
네, 물론이죠
Um, and then, uh, we then just call test a test where I'm going to use the improved function, and
그런 다음 테스트를 호출하죠 개선된 함수를 사용해서요 테스트를
we pass in the test and like some kind of a soap opera, I'm now, of course, going to say we will
통과합니다 드라마 같죠 다음 비디오에서 결과를 알려드리죠 get
get the results of this in the next video.
it get it
I will see you there.
거기서 봐요